ARNAB K. PAUL

Postdoctoral Research Associate at Oak Ridge National Laboratory

@ akpaul [at] vt [dot] edu Oak Ridge, TN, U.S.A.

+1 (540) 998 - 1480 % https://arnabkrpaul.github.io/

a Advanced Data and Workflow Group, ORNL





RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Research Associate

Oak Ridge National Laboratory Advanced Data and Workflow Group

Oak Ridge, TN, U.S.A.

• Applied AI technologies for large-scale HPC systems.

Graduate Research Intern

Crav Inc.

Mentor: Cory Spitz, Nathan Rutman (Cray), and Scott White (LANL)

Jun. 2019 - Aug. 2019

• Scalable metadata indexing for large scale distributed file systems.

Graduate Student Summer Intern (Computation Scholar)

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Advisor: Dr. Kathryn Mohror

May 2018 - Aug. 2018

♀ Livermore, CA, U.S.A.

- Analyze the metadata and job statistics of HPC I/O workloads.
- Build predictive models of I/O workloads based on the time series server data.

Graduate Student Summer Intern (Research Aide)

Argonne National Laboratory

Advisor: Dr. Ian Foster

May 2017 - Aug. 2017

• Built a scalable monitoring solution for arbitrary file systems.

Ph.D. Student @ Virginia Tech

Distributed Systems and Storage Laboratory

Advisor: Dr. Ali R. Butt

🛗 Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2020

- ♥ Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA, U.S.A.
- Optimizing containers in HPC storage systems.
- Load balancing in large scale storage systems, such as Lustre.
- Auto-tuning of parallelism in Spark

Masters Student @ National Institute of Technology, Rourkela Information Security and Data Communication Laboratory Advisor: Dr. Bibhudatta Sahoo

May 2014 - May 2015

NIT Rourkela, Odisha, India

• Dynamic virtual machine placement in cloud computing.

MENTORING EXPERIENCE

- Redwan Ibne Seraj Khan PhD, Virginia Tech, 2019 -
- Debasmita Biswas MS, Virginia Tech. 2020 -
- Subil Abraham MS, Virginia Tech, 2019 20
- Arpit Goyal MS, Virginia Tech, 2016 17

LIFE PHILOSOPHY

"Your best teacher is your last mistake." - Dr. A. P. J. Abdul Kalam

RESEARCH STATEMENT

I am a postdoctoral research associate at Oak Ridge National Laboratory. I recently completed my Ph.D. in Commputer Science from Virginia Tech. My research interests include high performance computing, applied machine learning, distributed file systems, cloud computing, distributed systems, and big data APIs.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Computer Science & Applications Virginia Tech

Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2020

Advisor: Dr. Ali R. Butt

• GPA: 4.0/4.0

M.S. in Computer Science & Applications Virginia Tech

Aug. 2015 - May 2018

GPA: 3.85/4.0

M.Tech. in Computer Science & Engineering National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

Aug. 2013 - May 2015

- Specialization: Software Engineering
- Advisor: Dr. Bibhudatta Sahoo
- GPA: 9.56/10.0

B.Tech. in Computer Science & Engineering **West Bengal University of Technology**

May 2009 - May 2013

GPA: 9.02/10.0

SKILLS

Lustre File System	Apache Spark
Containers Edge	Computing loT
C C++ JAVA	Python C#
SCALA MySQL	HTML CSS

UNIX | git | svn | latex | gnuplot

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Instructor (Virginia Tech) Aug. 2019 - Jan. 2020

• CS 2505: Intro Computer Organization - Fall 2019

Graduate Teaching Assistant (Virginia Tech) Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2019

- CS 3214: Operating Systems Spring 2019
- CS 5584: Network Security Fall 2018
- CS 3114: Data Structures and Algorithms *Spring 2018*
- CS 2506: Computer Org II Fall 2017
- CS 2114: Software Design and Data Structures - Fall 2016, Spring 2017
- CS 1054: Introduction to Programming in Java Fall 2015, Spring 2016

Graduate Teaching Assistant (NIT Rourkela) Aug. 2014 - May 2015

- CS 171: Computing Lab Autumn 2014, Spring 2015
- CS 670: Data Mining Lab Spring 2015

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Book Chapters

- Arnab K. Paul (2020). Edge or Cloud: What to Choose? Cloud Network Management: An IoT based Framework, Taylor Francis Group, CRC Press.
- Arnab Kumar Paul and Bibhudatta Sahoo (2017). Dynamic virtual machine placement in cloud computing. IGI Global, pp. 136–167.

Conference & Workshop Proceedings

- Abraham, Subil et al. (2020). "On the Use of Containers in High Performance Computing Environments". In: Proceedings of the IEEE International Conference on Cloud Computing (Cloud). IEEE.
- Arnab K. Paul, Olaf Faaland, et al. (2020). "Understanding HPC
 Application I/O Behavior Using System Level Statistics". In: HiPC.
 IEEE.
- Arnab K. Paul, Brian Wang, et al. (2020). "Efficient Metadata Indexing for HPC Storage Systems". In: 20th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Cluster, Cloud and Internet Computing (CCGrid). IEEE/ACM.
- Arnab K. Paul, Ryan Chard, et al. (2019). "FSMonitor: Scalable File System Monitoring for Arbitrary Storage Systems". In: 2019 IEEE Cluster. IEEE.
- Sim, Hyogi et al. (2019). "Cslim: Automated Extraction of IoT Functionalities from Legacy C Codebases". In: 2019 8th International Workshop on Computing and Networking for IoT and Beyond (ComNet-IoT), Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on Distributed Computing and Networking. ACM, pp. 421–426.
- Wadhwa, Bharti et al. (2019). "Resource Contention Aware Load Balancing for Large-Scale Parallel File Systems". In: 2019 33rd IEEE International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS). IEEE.
- Arnab K. Paul, Arpit Goyal, et al. (2017). "I/O load balancing for big data hpc applications". In: 2017 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data). IEEE, pp. 233–242.
- Arnab K. Paul, Steven Tuecke, et al. (2017). "Toward scalable monitoring on large-scale storage for software defined cyberinfrastructure". In: Proceedings of the 2nd Joint International Workshop on Parallel Data Storage & Data Intensive Scalable Computing Systems. ACM, pp. 49–54.
- Arnab Kumar Paul, Wenjie Zhuang, et al. (2016). "Chopper: Optimizing data partitioning for in-memory data analytics frameworks". In: 2016 IEEE International Conference on Cluster Computing (CLUSTER). IEEE, pp. 110–119.
- Arnab Kumar Paul, Sourav Kanti Addya, et al. (2014). "Application of greedy algorithms to virtual machine distribution across data centers". In: 11th IEEE India Conference INDICON 2014, Emerging Trends and Innovation of Technology. IEEE, pp. 1–6.

ACHIEVEMENTS

2020

- TBitshares Fellowship by CS @ VT
- Member of Dean's Graduate Team @ VT

2019

- Member of Association for India's Development
- ▲ Member of CS Graduate Council @ VT☑ Travel Grant IEEE Cluster '19
- ▲ Member of Dean's Graduate Team @ VT
- Student Volunteer, SC '19

2018

- P Bitshares Fellowship by CS @ VT
- Member of Dean's Graduate Team @ VT
- Student Volunteer, SCiNet @ SC '18

2017

President of Bengali Students' Ass. @ VT Travel Grant IEEE BigData '17

2016

Travel Grant IEEE Cluster '16

Student Volunteer, SC '16

2015

Gold Medalist, CS @ NITRKL

PROFESSIONAL SERVICES

PC Member

ICDCS 2020

Reviewer

- IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems - 2019, 2020
- Neural Processing Letters (NEPL) 2020
- Cluster Computing Journal 2019, 2020
- ASTESJ Journal 2018
- **I** IJGHPC Journal 2018, 2019, 2020
- AUTOSOFT Journal 2018
- MGS Journal 2017

External Reviewer

■ IEEE TSC Journal '18

■ BigData '17/'18, Cluster '17/'18/'20, ECOOP '20, HPDC '17/'18/'20, IC2E '17, ICCD '19, ICDCS '17/'18/'19, ICS '17/'18, IPDPS '18/'19/'20

REFEREES

Dr. Ali R. Butt

- @ butta@cs.vt.edu